We are doing now דף טו Daf Tes-Vav 15 but we start
at the bottom of יד עמוד ב. Yud-Daled Amud Bais. After the
משנה Mishnah had covered who are the few that שוחט, shocht, we
had discussed yesterday to begin discussing when can you שוחט. shocht. We
discussed nighttime, that is בדיעבד b'di'eved if there is not sufficient lighting,
and then we discussed
שבת, Shabbos, that even if a person violates שבת, Shabbos, if they
שוחט shocht on שבת, Shabbos, the שחיטה shechita is valid. That led
תוספות Tosafos to two interesting observations. Number one, the person is not
identified as a מומר לחלל שבת, mumar l'chalal Shabbos, which would make
the שחיטה shechita invalid, and he says that's because the status of
מומר לחלל שבת mumar l'chalal Shabbos means a habitual שבת Shabbos violator,
not a one-time שבת Shabbos violator. And the other interesting observation תוספות
Tosafos made is, why can you eat the meat? Okay, you don't
want to cook it, that's your business, but what about all the
blood in it? And תוספות Tosafos pointed out that as long as
the blood remains absorbed within the meat, it's not yet considered blood.
So you could actually eat raw meat without removing the blood. The
only reason we salt the meat is because when you cook it,
the blood will come out and get reabsorbed. But if you're eating
it raw or broiling it, you do not have to get all
of the blood out. Two very interesting principles that are derived from
this משנה, Mishnah, but the גמרא Gemara focused on the point that
there was a statement of רב Rav that according to רב יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, to be determined, you cannot eat the meat on that
day itself of שבת Shabbos itself. And most of yesterday was devoted
to figuring out that this might be a רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
about מוקצה muktzeh and that since the meat was not fit to
be eaten before שבת, Shabbos, it could not be eaten on שבת
Shabbos itself even if the שחיטה shechita was valid. So we are
going to continue today with determining which רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would
lead to the fact that the meat cannot be eaten on the
day itself. Charlie?
Here they don't just discuss the permissibility of eating raw meat, which
actually came up in a previous מסכתא masechta with some very negative
comments towards people who eat raw meat.
Right, that's a good
point, about the Alexandrian כהנים Kohanim who were called the Babylonian. Right,
it's not a question about permissibility; it's a question about whether it
was uncouth or not, but right, but technically it's permissible. So that's
why that's a good point, the גמרא Gemara did not comment on
that. But תוספות Tosafos at least commented on the halachic aspects about
what happened to the blood. Okay, so now we pick up on
the bottom of יד עמוד ב Yud-Daled Amud Bais and where it
says אמר
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי.
Amar Rav
Sheshes Brei D'rav Idi. So it is five lines from the bottom
line, starts with the word בריה, Brei, בריה דרב אידי. Brei D'rav
Idi. So we're still trying to identify according to which רב יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda can you not eat this meat on שבת Shabbos itself
and now we're wrapping up the possibility that it has to do
with a מוקצה muktzeh problem. So let's take a look. אמר רב
ששת בריה דרב אידי, Amar Rav Sheshes Brei D'rav Idi, רב יהודה
דנרות היא. Rebbi Yehuda d'neros hi. It's the רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
about lamps. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braitah, again about
an issue about מוקצה muktzeh on שבת. Shabbos. מטלטלין נר חדש אבל
לא ישן דברי רב יהודה. Metaltelin ner chadash aval lo yashan divrei
Rebbi Yehuda. You can move a brand new lamp that has never
been used, but not an old one, right, because the old thing,
I mean look, we all know what it's like on חנוכה Chanukah
if you use oil מנורות, menorahs, right, after when you have to
clean them out. They're oily, they're yucky, and especially if you've used
them for a while, it's copper, it could be all charred and
have all of that whatever, all the black stuff that comes from
a burning candle. So basically it's what's called מאוס, ma'us, disgusting. And
this is a category of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס, muktzeh machmas miyus, something
that is מוקצה muktzeh because it's disgusting, you don't want to handle
it. Okay, so therefore he says you cannot move those types of
lamps on שבת; Shabbos; they're מוקצה. muktzeh. And we're assuming that if
you're concerned about מוקצה מחמת מיאוס, muktzeh machmas miyus, you'd also be
concerned about something like this animal that if you can't use it
on שבת, Shabbos, when שבת Shabbos began it hadn't been שוחט, shocht,
it would make it מוקצה. muktzeh. So let's take a look. דברי
רב
יהודה, Divrei Rebbi Yehuda, that's what רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says. So
the גמרא Gemara retorts, אימר דשמעת ליה לרב יהודה, Eima deshmat leih
l'Rebbi Yehuda, when did רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda say that there was
a problem במוקצה מחמת מיאוס, b'muktzeh machmas miyus, something that is מוקצה
muktzeh because it is disgusting? מוקצה מחמת איסור מי שמעת ליה? Muktzeh
machmas issur mi shamat leih? Where did you ever hear that he
had a problem and finally, after an entire דף daf yesterday, the
גמרא Gemara finally labels this to be the problem it is, which
is מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzeh machmas issur. The cow when שבת Shabbos
begins is מוקצה. muktzeh. Why is it מוקצה? muktzeh? Because you are
not allowed to use it on שבת. Shabbos. You can't שוחט shocht
it, you can't plow your field with it. Okay, so a cow
when שבת Shabbos begins is מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzeh machmas issur. It
is something not able to be used because of the שבת Shabbos
prohibition. So what? You cannot milk it. I mean maybe you can
milk it צער בעלי חיים tzar ba'alei chayim with have a non-Jew
milk it or something, but you have no legitimate use for this,
it's מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzeh machmas issur. Okay, so how did where
did we ever hear that רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda had that problem?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אין, In, yes, we do know he
has a problem. דתנן, D'tnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, top
of טו עמוד א, Tes-Vav Amud Aleph, רב יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda
omer, רב יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says, כל כלי נר שמתכת מטלטלין, kol
kli ner shematachas metaltelin, you can move all types of metal נר
ner of metal lamps because before we were talking actually about, I
didn't mention this, pottery. So the pottery, it really gets the oil
gets into the crevices, it really gets ugly and charred. That becomes
disgusting. Metal does not become so disgusting. So metal lamps are not
מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. muktzeh machmas miyus. Those you can move.
איסור *issur*. Now obviously now that is a different type of מוקצה
מחמת איסור muktzah machmas isur. *muktzeh machmas issur*,
because there, like if you think about a cow, I can't use
a cow because I have no, you know, there's no use for
it on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. By a candle, you know, there is
a use for a candle. You can't read by a candle but
obviously a candle can light your room. There's no prohibition to use
a candle. So the concept of מוקצה muktzah. מחמת איסור *muktzeh machmas
issur* by a candle is not so, it's not precise or it's
not the same. What it might mean is that well the candle
was doing an איסור *issur* when שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* began, it was
doing a מלאכה melacha *melacha*, it was burning. So the fact that
it was doing a מלאכה melacha *melacha* makes it off limits. Another
possible way to understand it is that the whole concept of מוקצה
muktzah. *muktzeh* is a concept about moving things, right? מוקצה muktzah, *muktzeh*,
I mean when we're kids we say, ooh I can't, you know,
you touched the car, you're מוקצה muktzah. *muktzeh* or something like that.
I remember that the whole cooties of מוקצה muktzah, *muktzeh*, but what
מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* really means is a prohibition of moving things. So
you can't move a burning candle, right, because that might cause it
to go out. But this actually is an interesting question that the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* considers, the idea of a burning candle something of
מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh*, and it raises interesting questions. For example, if I
have a halogen lamp that's connected that's in this corner and I
need to move it to another corner, you know with a long
wire, right? Can I go ahead and move it on שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbos*, you know, from one place to another? It's not going to
cause it to flicker and go out. It's a halogen lamp for
God's sake. Okay, but is it considered to be מוקצה muktzah. מחמת
איסור *muktzeh machmas issur* because it was essentially a burning fire when
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* began? Okay, so that's not so clear why this
is considered to be that but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes it's
in the same category. So it says what? Can you move the
lamp? Most people will say no based on the analogy here to
the candle, but a lot of it has to do with if
it's on. If it's off and you need the room, the space,
that's a different category. Then it's a כלי k'li, שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli
shemlachto l'issur*. But if it was on and burning, okay, but again
that's actually it is debated because the question is why you understand
that the burning candle is considered מוקצה muktzah מחמת איסור *muktzeh machmas
issur*. What's the concern of moving it or is it the fact
that it was actually burning and doing a מלאכה melacha *melacha*?
Okay, you can't read by a שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* candle?
Correct, because you might come to tip it. Why can we read
by these lights? Because these lights you don't come to tip. Interesting
question about what would we say if you had let's say a
lamp, a reading lamp, that had an adjustable knob to it? Would
that be analogous to that prohibition? Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says
you can't tip it once you use
because then you're causing it to burn. No, also you're increasing the
flow of oil so that's considered הבערה *havara*. הבערה *havara* is not
just creating the fire.
Why can't you just move it like that?
Oh, just moving is a, so that's not the issue of reading
by it. That's just the issue of moving. If you're reading and
the light isn't so good and you try to jiggle it to
get the light better, that's increasing the burning. A candle, why can't
you just move it? A burning candle. A burning candle. There the
concern is that the act of moving will cause it to blow
out or cause it to burn at a different rate. That's what
we're going to see right here. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so you see that he has a
problem of מוקצה muktzah? מחמת איסור *muktzeh machmas issur* and it should
be the same problem with the cow. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ודילמא שאני התם דהוא דחי ליה בידיים *v'dilma shani hasam d'hu
dachai lei b'yadayim*.
So you are, when you light a candle ערב שבת erev Shabbos.
*erev Shabbos*, you are pushing it away. You are making it מוקצה
muktzah מחמת איסור *muktzeh machmas issur* and you're so actively sort of
putting it out of your reach on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. A cow
that just you never pushed out of your reach, it just has
the problem, maybe that is not a מוקצה muktzah *muktzeh* problem. So
at this stage the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is not willing to conclude
that the cow is מוקצה muktzah, *muktzeh*, okay, which is completely blah,
because if you ask anybody, right, what's, I mean my god, you
know, there's a whole problem nowadays about people want to have pets
and is a pet מוקצה muktza. *muktzeh*? Okay, and there there's a
whole debate because some גמרות *Gemaras* sound like it is, but maybe
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was talking about cases of farm animals and
not about pets, you know, which actually do serve, you know, serve
a purpose and they're used for companionship and so on. But for
God's sake, a cow, of course a cow is מוקצה muktza *muktzeh*.
It's מוקצה muktza מחמת איסור *muktzeh machmas issur*. And the other thing
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* suggested yesterday that was it נולד *nolad* also
sounds absurd. One day it's moo the next day it's meat and
you're saying that's not נולד *nolad*, that's not something new? But for
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has at least and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*
says it, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says this is the דחויא בעלמא *dehuya
b'alma*. Of course if we have a problem of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס
muktzah machmas me-us, *muktzeh machmas mius*, we have a problem of מוקצה
muktza. מחמת איסור *muktzeh machmas issur*, there's no question that this cow
is מוקצה muktza *muktzeh*, okay, but for some reason the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has tried to say, well maybe not necessarily according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*. You can't absolutely prove it. And that's
going to lead it to the focus today which is to explore
a different position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda*. But what
we tried now is say that this cow even though the שחיטה
shechita *shechita* was good on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*, you can't eat it
on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* itself, why not because of מוקצה muktza. *muktzeh*,
although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tried to argue it might not be
מוקצה muktza *muktzeh*. In it it definitely is מוקצה muktza, *muktzeh* and
that's what תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says but we're bracketing that for now
and we're going to look at another reason why you can't eat
this cow on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So let's take a look.
It's not מוקצה muktza *muktzeh*, it's not this type of מוקצה muktza
*muktzeh*.
Well but they're saying because it's not this type of מוקצה muktza
*muktzeh* you can't prove that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* would
say it's מוקצה muktza. *muktzeh*. And the argument was was that it
would be a problem of... according to ר' יהודה. Reb Yehuda Right,
but תוספות Tosfos, says, no, if ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda has a
problem of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס, muktzah machmas me-us anybody who's got a
problem with מוקצה muktza. מחמת מיאוס definitely has a problem with מוקצה
muktza מחמת איסור. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos just says with the ר'
יהודהs Reb Yehuda. that we've put forward, it's impossible to imagine that
this would not also be מוקצה. muktza Okay, but for whatever reason
the גמרא Gemara is saying you can't prove it, and therefore it's
not necessarily this ר' יהודה. Reb Yehuda Yes.
You're saying there was a ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda
that does this issue? I'm just wondering...
Well because רב Rav made a statement that this meat that you
שחט shechted on שבת, Shabbat, while the שחיטה shechita was כשר, kosher,
according to ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda? you can't eat it on שבת.
Shabbat So we're trying to figure out what was רב Rav talking
about? Which ר' יהודה? Reb Yehuda. Okay, so now we're going to
go... Yeah, there are a couple of statements of ר' יהודה. Reb
Yehuda So now we're going to talk about... I don't mean which
person, but which statement of his. So now we're going to talk
about a different approach to why you can't eat it that's not
related to מוקצה. muktza, So let's take a look.
Okay, so it says the following. It says: אלא אמר
רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, four lines from the top דף
קנו עמוד א, daaf kuf nun vuv amud aleph, rather says רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda דמבשל de-mevashel היא, hee, he
has a different approach. It's ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda, about cooking on
שבת. Shabbat. And the problem here is not מוקצה, muktza problem here
is another category called מעשה שבת. ma-aseh Shabbos. That if you through
a מלאכה melacha make something...
change something's status and make something able to be benefited from, you
cannot benefit from a מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbat on שבת Shabbat.
itself. Okay, so that is a prohibition according to most תנאים Tana-im
it's rabbinic, we don't want you to be benefiting from a מלאכה
on שבת Shabbos; because then you'll come to do the מלאכה on
שבת. Shabbos, According to ר' יוחנן הסנדלר Reb Yochanan HaSandlar it's biblical.
It's that you cannot sort of benefit from something that is the
product of a sin. Okay, but this is a category called, you
know, מעשה שבת, ma-aseh Shabbos, benefiting from a מלאכה on שבת Shabbos
and that's the problem. You slaughtered it, the שחיטה shechita was כשר,
kosher, but if you were to eat it on שבת Shabbos you
would be benefiting from a violation of שבת, Shabbos and therefore if
you wait until after שבת Shabbos you're really not benefiting, right, because
I could have slaughtered it after שבת. Shabbos But if I'm eating
it on שבת Shabbos. then I'm benefiting from an actual violation of
שבת. Shabbos So it's that ר' יהודה, Reb Yehuda it's not related
to מוקצה. muktza Let's take a look at that. ר' יהודה Reb
Yehuda about cooking. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a משנה: Mishna: המבשל
בשבת, Hamvashel b-Shabbos, if somebody cooks on שבת; Shabbos בשוגג, beshogeg, if
they did it unintentionally, they forgot it was שבת, Shabbos they forgot
that you were forbidden to cook, יאכל, yochal, you can eat it;
במזיד, bemezid, if it was intentionally, לא יאכל, lo yochal, it cannot
be eaten; דברי ר' מאיר. divrei Reb Meir. That's what ר' מאיר
Reb Meir says. ר' יהודה אומר, Reb Yehuda omer, so ר' יהודה
Reb Yehuda says, this is going to be the position we're going
to focus on: בשוגג יאכל למוצאי שבת, beshogeg yochal l-motzei Shabbos, I
agree if it's unintentional you can eat, but not on שבת Shabbat
itself, on מוצאי שבת. motzei Shabbos. So again notice the relevance for
us. It would mean that on שבת Shabbos, itself it cannot be
eaten, which was the claim, the שחיטה shechita during שבת Shabbos. itself
cannot be eaten on שבת Shabbos. itself. So he says even if
it was unintentional it cannot be eaten until after שבת Shabbos, because
otherwise you'd be deriving benefit; במזיד, bemezid, if it was willful, לא
יאכל עולמית, lo yochal olamis, you can never eat from it because
then you are a willful violator, you can never benefit from it.
It's a fine, it's a קנס. knas. That's what he says. Now,
ר' יוחנן הסנדלר Reb Yochanan HaSandlar introduces, says a stronger statement, but
also introduces two factors that we had not been considering. So let's
take a look, or at least one factor. ר' יוחנן הסנדלר אומר,
Reb Yochanan HaSandlar omer, ר' יוחנן הסנדלר Reb Yochanan HaSandlar says,
בשוגג, beshogeg, if it's unintentional, יאכל למוצאי שבת. yochal l-motzei Shabbos. Then
after שבת. Shabbos. Sounds similar to what ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda said.
But here's a qualifier: לאחרים, la-acherim,
only for other people, for the non-violator,
ולא לו, v-lo lo, you, actually violated, you can never eat this
stuff, even if you only did it בשוגג. beshogeg. במזיד, Bemezid, if
it was willful, לא יאכל עולמית, lo yochal olamis, can never be
eaten, לא לו, lo lo, not for the one who violated, ולא
לאחרים, v-lo la-acherim, and not for anybody else. So ר' יוחנן הסנדלר
Reb Yochanan HaSandlar is very strict, right? He says if it's willful,
nobody can violate... nobody can eat it even somebody who did not
do it, an innocent person. So therefore in another place when the
גמרא Gemara. analyzes this it says ר' יוחנן הסנדלר Reb Yochanan HaSandlar
basically understands this to be a biblical principle, it says קדש היא
לכם, kodesh hee lachem, so that שבת Shabbos is holy, the same
way that שבת Shabbos is holy what products of שבת Shabbos are
holy, holy not in the positive sense but meaning off-limits. So anything
that is the product of a willful violation of שבת Shabbos is
the product of a sin, certainly if it's a willful violation it's
off-limits to everybody, I don't care if you're the one who did
it or not the one who did it. That's ר' יוחנן הסנדלר.
Reb Yochanan HaSandlar. Other cases when it's unintentional or the other תנאים
Tana-im that are not so strict, they understand that those are cases
more about
rabbinic גזירות gezeiros and safeguards and not benefiting, etc., but all at
the rabbinic level not at the biblical level. Now what is missing
is ר' יוחנן הסנדלר Reb Yochanan HaSandlar told us what he thinks
about the difference between the perpetrator and other people. That is missing
from the statements of ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda and ר' מאיר. Reb
Meir. Okay, and that leads to a big discussion in the ראשונים
Rishonim about which parts of ר' יהודה and ר' מאיר's Reb Meir
statements are talking about the perpetrator and which are talking about other
people. So I'm going to go back and read it to you
the way רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosfos understand what their statements are
talking about. It's a critical part that's missing from the context of
their statements. So we'll go back and read it and I'll explain
it to you, but first Charlie has a question.
I was going to ask if this
made...
Well, your animals you are deriving benefit and for רבי יוחנן הסנדלר
Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar it is about deriving benefit. It's not just about
eating. To give it to, let's say, an animal that is not
yours or somebody who is a non-Jew who is not somebody that
you know, so there will not be any reciprocity or whatever, right,
that would not be prohibited, but you could not sell it. Okay,
that's according to רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar that says this
sort of very strictly. Now, let's go back and read this משנה
Mishna again, and I will tell you how again, it's debatable obviously
and it is debated, but I will tell you how it's read
by רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot the other opinions, with the question
of to whom are we talking about, the perpetrator or others. So
let's take a look. I'll read it again. דתנן המבשל בשבת, Detnan
hamivashel beShabbos, again, four lines from the top or five lines. המבשל
בשבת, Hamivashel beShabbos, if you cook on שבת, Shabbos בשוגג יאכל במזיד
לא יאכל דברי רבי מאיר. beshogeig yochal bimeizid lo yochal divrei Rabbi
Meir. So בשוגג, beshogeig, if you did it unintentionally, so you, even
you yourself can eat. The way רש"י Rashi reads it, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is the most lenient. If it was unintentional, then nobody,
then nothing. Even the perpetrator can eat. Okay, no consequences if it
was unintentional. Okay, if it was במזיד, bimeizid, if it was willful,
לא יאכל, lo yochal, and this רש"י Rashi says means nobody can
eat, but only means, what else is missing here is the time
limit. So רש"י Rashi also inserts nobody can eat till מוצאי שבת.
Motzei Shabbos. Okay, so if it was willful then it's a problem
of deriving benefit. It's not a problem of fining you or punishing
you or whatever, although it could be, it's not. It's a problem
of deriving benefit, and since it's a problem of deriving benefit, nobody
can eat, neither you or anybody else, but only until מוצאי שבת.
Motzei Shabbos. That's how he reads
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, now תוספות has
a nice little mnemonic. The מזיד meizid of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is the שוגג shogeig of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda, Okay, what did
we just say רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said? If you did it
willful, it's a problem of deriving benefit, nobody can derive benefit till
after שבת. Shabbos That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
when it's בשוגג. beshogeig. בשוגג, Beshogeig, if it's unintentional, יאכל למוצאי שבת.
yochal lemotzei Shabbos. Then you or others, it can only be eaten
by anyone until מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. That's the problem of deriving
benefit, but for him he has a problem even if it's שוגג,
shogeig, so we have to wait till after
שבת. Shabbos במזיד, Bimeizid, if it's willful, לא יאכל עולמית. lo yochal
olamis. Now that is very harsh. Never be eaten. That's only for
the perpetrator. Okay, and so and that is essentially what רבי יוחנן
הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar says by שוגג. shogeig. Let's look at רבי
יוחנן הסנדלר. Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar. רבי יוחנן הסנדלר אומר בשוגג, Rabbi Yochanan
Hasandlar omer beshogeig, unintentional, יאכל למוצאי שבת לאחרים ולא לו. yochal lemotzei
Shabbos laacherim velo lo. Other people can eat it after שבת, Shabbos,
and לא לו, velo lo, you can never eat it. So רבי
יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar says בשוגג beshogeig you can never eat
it, which was what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said by במזיד. bimeizid.
If it's מזיד, meizid, you can never eat it. So תוספות has
a great mnemonic, right, and it's important because these critical things are
missing from here. He says everybody is one step built, you know,
everybody is one shifted from the previous person. So רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir מזיד meizid is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
שוגג, shogeig, and רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda מזיד meizid is רבי יוחנן
הסנדלר's Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar שוגג. shogeig. Okay, but anyway what do we
have? We have that for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda if it is
בשוגג, beshogeig, everybody has to wait till מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. And
that fits in with רב's Rav statement that even though the שחיטה
shchita was כשרה, kashera, you have to wait till מוצאי שבת. Motzei
Shabbos.
But it doesn't say בשוגג beshogeig over there.
Well, one minute, we're going to get to that. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So that, that's what רב Rav was
talking about, very nice, has nothing to do with מוקצה, muktza had
to do with benefiting from
שבת. Shabbos So now the גמרא Gemara says ונוקמה במזיד ורבי מאיר.
venukma bimeizid veRabbi Meir. Ah, so you said according to, that's רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda. שוגג, shogeig, right? רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda שוגג shogeig
is everybody waits till מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. But as we've just
said, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda. שוגג shogeig is רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
מזיד. meizid.
So why don't we be saying people are doing...
okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara finally, let's see what the
גמרא. Gemara Why don't we say that if we have to wait
till tomorrow, why
don't we say that it means that you are a willful violator
of שבת Shabbos and you're waiting till tomorrow because that's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says when you're מזיד
meizid then everybody waits till מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. So why don't
we say it's a case of מזיד ורבי מאיר? meizid veRabbi Meir?
לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka dachach. Doesn't make sense. דקתני, diktani, because
it says if you שחט shachted it on שבת Shabbos. or on
יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. דומיא דיום הכיפורים. dumya deYom HaKippurim.
It says שבת Shabbos, or יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, meaning that the
case of שבת Shabbos is analogous to יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. And
this, by the way, presumably is what motivated רב Rav to say
you can't eat it on שבת Shabbos itself. Because it says שבת
Shabbos and יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, so it's just like יום הכיפורים.
Yom HaKippurim. Same way on יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim you obviously can't
eat it because it's יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. He assumed that also
on שבת Shabbos itself you cannot be eating it. So שבת דומיא
דיום הכיפורים. Shabbos dumya deYom HaKippurim. מה יום הכיפורים לא שנא בשוגג
ולא שנא במזיד, Mah Yom HaKippurim lo shena beshogeig velo shena bimeizid,
on יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, I don't care if you שחט shachted
it on שוגג shogeig or במזיד, bimeizid, you can't eat it because
it's יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. You can't eat anything. So the same
way on יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim nobody can eat and under no
circumstances that it's slaughtered can it be eaten. So therefore אף הכא
נמי, af hacha nami, here too when it was slaughtered on שבת,
Shabbos לא שנא בשוגג ולא שנא במזיד לא אכיל, lo shena beshogeig
velo shena bimeizid lo achil, whether שוגג shogeig or מזיד meizid cannot
be eaten. Okay, so therefore we are saying that רב Rav was
motivated. So who is an opinion to say it can't be eaten
on the day itself because it was compared to יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, and therefore he said and the same way on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur doesn't matter how it got slaughtered, שוגג shogig or מזיד
meizid can't be eaten. So here too, so who is an opinion
that says that no matter even if it was done unintentionally, it
cannot be eaten on the day itself by anybody, that is רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, says בשוגג b'shogig nobody can
eat it on the day itself, so that's why he said our
משנה Mishna was רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda So now the גמרא Gemara
says one minute,
ומי מצית מוקמת לה בשוגג כרבי יהודה, umi matzit mokmat lah b'shogig
k'Rabbi Yehuda, how can you say our משנה Mishna is talking about
שוגג shogig and that motivated you to say it's רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. who said even by שוגג shogig you can't eat it on
the day itself, והא אף על פי שמתחייב בנפשו קתני? v'ha af
al pi she'mitchayev b'nafsho tani? The משנה Mishna says if you slaughter
an animal on שבת Shabbos even though you are liable with your
soul, you did a capital sin, it still is כשר. koshair. So
if it says what you did was a capital sin, it sounds
like you did it במזיד. b'meizid. I want you to say במזיד,
b'meizid, say we're talking according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So the
גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is how what the
משנה Mishna means. אף על פי שבמזיד מתחייב בנפשו, af al pi
d'b'meizid mitchayev b'nafsho, even though this is a type of sin that
would have a capital punishment were you to have done it willfully,
so הכא דבשוגג שחיטתו כשרה. hocha d'bishogig shchitaso k'shira. Here you did
it only on שוגג, shogig, so it's a type of a sin
that's a capital sin, you did not do the actual capital offense
because you did not do it willfully, you only did it בשוגג.
b'shogig. And therefore the שחיטה כשרה, shchitas koshair, but you just can't
eat it on the day itself, you can eat it after. If
you had done it willfully, then you might be completely off limits
depending on how you פסקן pasken רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, רבי יוחנן הסנדלר, Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar, right according to but
since you only did it unintentionally it's only אסור assur on שבת
Shabbos itself, you can eat it after שבת. Shabbos Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara is going to wrap this up but it pretty
much seems happy with this explanation of the
משנה. Mishna. ונוקמה כרבי יוחנן הסנדלר, v'nokmah k'Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar, one minute,
if you want the meat to be off limits even on שוגג
shogig even based on שוגג shogig on שבת, Shabbos how about
רבי יוחנן הסנדלר? Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar? דאמר לא שנא בשוגג ולא שנא
במזיד לא אכיל, d'amar lo shana b'shogig v'lo shana b'meizid lo achil,
who says even whether שוגג shogig or מזיד meizid you can never
eat the meat on שבת Shabbos itself. Okay, remember what did רבי
יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar say? He said that if it's שוגג
shogig it's off limits to everybody on שבת Shabbos itself, and מוצאי
שבת motzei Shabbos the person who willfully did it can never eat
it. Right? So the willful violator can never eat it. So why
not say it's רבי יוחנן הסנדלר? Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar? He also has
it off limits to everybody on שבת Shabbos itself. So the גמרא
Gemara says
לא אכיל, lo achil, no, רבי יוחנן הסנדלר קמיפלג דמוצאי שבת לאחרים
ולא לו. Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar kamiflig d'motzei Shabbos l'achairim v'lo lo. No,
because רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar exactly that point, he's more
strict when it comes to מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbos as opposed to
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, who says right that if it's בשוגג b'shogig
nobody eats it but after שבת Shabbos שלום על ישראל, shalom al
Yisrael, רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan HaSandlar says that if it's בשוגג
b'shogig on שבת Shabbos, nobody eats it but after שבת Shabbos. the
perpetrator can never eat it. Okay that's a problem because the משנה
Mishna says שחיטתו כשרה, shchitaso k'shaira, the שחיטה shchita is כשר. koshair.
So even if you read it to mean you have to wait
a day, but when you say כשר koshair means eventually anybody can
eat from the meat. And according to רבי יוחנן הסנדלר Rabbi Yochanan
HaSandlar there'll be one person who can never eat from the meat,
the guy who actually was the perpetrator. תנא דידן Tana didan our
תנא Tanna שחיטתו כשרה קתני. shchitaso k'shaira tani. It says the שחיטה
Shchita is כשר. koshair. So even if you can't eat it on
שבת Shabbos. because of a שבת הלכה, Shabbos halacha, eventually it's going
to be a כשר שחיטה. koshair shchita. לא שנא לו ולא שנא
לאחרים, lo shna lo v'lo shna l'achairim, it doesn't matter for you
or for others, anybody will be able to eat from the meat.
So here we are saying and the גמרא Gemara actually seems quite
happy with this answer, that because the משנה Mishna says שבת Shabbos,
or יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it means that שבת Shabbos, is like
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that the meat can't be eaten on that
day and it doesn't matter whether it was שחט בשוגג או במזיד,
shechted b'shogig o b'meizid, but because it says שחיטתו כשרה shchitaso k'shaira
that also means that eventually everybody will be able to eat from
that meat, even the guy that שחט shechted it. So where is
there an opinion that says you can't eat from the meat on
שבת Shabbos regardless of שוגג shogig or מזיד meizid but after שבת
Shabbos, you can eat from it? So that would be רבי יהודה.
Rebbi Yehuda, Where it says בשוגג b'shogig it's off limits to everybody
because you're benefiting, but after שבת Shabbos at least if it was
בשוגג b'shogig everybody can eat from it, even the one who שחט
shechted it himself. Okay, so that's what we have now explained and
we've introduced this principle about מעשה שבת. Ma'aseh Shabbos. Now the גמרא
Gemara is actually going to turn to the הלכה halacha about מעשה
שבת Ma'aseh Shabbos which is very important להלכה. l'halacha.
This is an anonymous משנה Mishna and there's a general rule that
most anonymous משניות Mishnayos are
הלכה halacha by רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir.
So I guess they don't feel like they need to.
Right, that's true, you know, it's we assume it's רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir unless we somehow have a reason to say otherwise.
And they've given a reason.
Although, I agree with you, the reason does not seem so amazingly
strong, but for whatever reason Rav either out of tradition or was
persuaded by the comparison of שבת Shabbos, to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
but you're right, there's no it does not seem like such a
compelling reason. But this is Rav's statement, we're trying to understand what
Rav was saying. Okay, so now because we're on this whole discussion
about מעשה שבת Ma'aseh Shabbos and also about Rav's position, we are
going to wrap it up a little bit and this is very
important להלכה. l'halacha. So let's take a look. Okay,
תני תנא קמיה דרב, tani tanna kamei d'Rav, so a תנא Tanna
taught in front of רב, Rav, a תנא Tanna here is the
person that has all of the משניות Mishnayos and ברייתות Braisos memorized.
he would be like the library, so he taught the following ברייתא
braisa in the presence of רב: Rav: המבשל בשבת בשוגג יאכל במזיד
לא יאכל. Hamivashail b'Shabbos, b'shogeg yochel, b'meizid lo yochel. If somebody cooks
on שבת, Shabbos so if it was בשוגג b'shogeg it can be
eaten, במזיד b'meizid and intentionally it cannot be eaten. Who is that?
That is רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. That's the most lenient opinion, that
בשוגג b'shogeg no problem, the only problem is במזיד, b'meizid, and even
במזיד b'meizid is only can't be eaten like till מוצאי שבת Motzei
Shabbos etc. Okay. What? Yeah, yeah, but we're reading it at least
that phrase was taken straight from רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. However we
framed רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, that was a quote of רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir, which was the most lenient that בשוגג b'shogeg anybody can
eat from it, okay, and even on שבת. Shabbos So that's what
the תנא Tanna taught. So where am I, במזיד לא יאכל. b'meizid
lo yochel. ומשתקי ליה רב, u'mashtikei lei Rav, and רב Rav says,
shh, quiet, don't say that. So מאי טעמא משתקי ליה, mai ta'ama
mashtikei lei, why did רב Rav silence him? אילימא משום דסבירא ליה
כרבי יהודה, eileima mishum d'svira lei k'Rebbi Yehuda,
maybe because he personally rules more strictly, like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda?
that's the one he said was the משנה mishna anyway, although that
doesn't mean he rules like it, but maybe he rules like רבי
יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda more strict position, that on בשוגג b'shogeg even בשוגג
b'shogeg you have to wait till after
שבת. Shabbat. ותנא תני כרבי מאיר, v'tana tani k'Rebbi Meir, and the
תנא Tanna taught like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. So and therefore he
didn't like hearing what the תנא Tanna had to say cause that
wasn't his ruling. So he says, give me a break, you know,
משום דסבירא ליה כרבי יהודה, mishum d'svira lei k'Rebbi Yehuda, just cause
you hold like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. מאן דתני כרבי מאיר משתקי
ליה, man d'tani k'Rebbi Meir mashtikei lei, somebody who teaches רבי מאיר's
Rebbi Meir position you're going to go silence them?
I mean, in these days it happens all the time.
Okay, well whatever but the point is, anyway רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
wasn't a competing authority, it wasn't like he was teaching something that
שמואל Shmuel ruled and שמואל Shmuel ruled against רב Rav and it
was רב's Rav בית מדרש. beis medrash. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was
a תנא. Tanna. So רב Rav was quite aware of the different
opinions of the תנאים Tannaim and you know just and even if
you're going to rule like one of them, since when does an
אמורא Amora not willing to present all the different opinions of the
תנאים. Tannaim. So just because you don't rule like it is no
reason to silence the תנא. Tanna. So that's so, that can't be
why. So so let's keep on going. אילימא eileima what did we
just say? Okay. סבירא ליה כרבי יהודה. svira lei k'Rebbi Yehuda. מאן
דסבירא ליה כרבי מאיר משתקי ליה? man d'svira lei k'Rebbi Meir mashtikei
lei? ואף, v'af, and in addition, מי סבר לה כרבי יהודה, mi
savar lah k'Rebbi Yehuda, and anyway who since when does רב Rav
hold like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda We actually happen to know that
רב Rav holds like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. He holds leniently. How
do you know? דאמר רב חנן בר אמי, d'amar Rav Chanan bar
Ami, and רב חנן בר אמי Rav Chanan bar Ami said, and
here is a fascinating other sort of aspect of פסק, psak, כי
מורי להו רב לתלמידיה, ki morei lehu Rav l'talmidei, when רב Rav
would give a פסק psak to his students, מורי להו כרבי מאיר,
morei lehu k'Rebbi Meir, he would פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir leniently. וכי דרש בפרקא, v'chi darash b'pirka, but when he would
give a public lecture on שבת, Shabbos so to the you know
to the laity, to to everybody, so דרש כרבי יהודה, darash k'Rebbi
Yehuda, he would actually give a he would actually expound רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda position
because it was more strict cause he basically was concerned that like
you can't trust people with the leniencies of רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir.
My students I can trust, they're very you know scrupulous, it's not
going to lead to other leniencies, but for the common people like
if you give that פסק psak it's going to lead to them
to not be careful. This idea by the way about not trusting
people with פסק הלכה psak halacha when you do it in a
public forum is you know is sort of very much embodied today
by these English handbooks which are you know הלכה halacha handbooks where
they're very very strict, right? They always take the strictest positions as
a general rule and then sometimes in the footnotes in Hebrew they
tell you, you know what some of the other possible leniencies are
with the assumption that if you're smart enough to read the Hebrew
and you're a big enough תלמיד חכם talmid chacham to understand it,
that then we can trust you with the leniencies. But otherwise we
can't. The problem is in Israel since everybody can read Hebrew they
still do it. The leniencies are still like if you read שמירת
שבת כהלכתה, Shemiras Shabbos K'hilchasa, right? In the footnotes, that's where the
leniencies are. So the funny thing is though if you're reading it
presumably you can read the footnotes. But still I think there's an
assumption that footnotes they're dense, you know who bothers with the footnotes.
So anyway but anyway this is an interesting issue about you know
the question about something that I think for us in the you
know does not sit well. But the question sort of about
like transparency and trusting people with the information as opposed to controlling
the information. There is the counterbalances is that you know there are
sometimes realities about this. Very often you know a רב rav who
פסקנ'ס paskens something to somebody, you know what what you פסקן pasken
as a בדיעבד b'diavad case all of a sudden once it's פסקנ'ד
paskened and certainly once it becomes public, so you know all the
the בדיעבד b'diavad becomes a לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So there is a certain
reality to that but it it does raise interesting questions about you
know control of information and so on. This is definitely a phenomenon
in the גמרא. Gemara Sometimes it's expressed as הלכה ואין מורין כן,
halacha v'ein morin kein, but הלכה ואין מורין כן halacha v'ein morin
kein means even like more even to your like students. Here it's
a different issue of one פסק psak to the students and a
more strict פסק psak to in to sort of to the general
public. Again it doesn't necessarily mean that if somebody came to him
with a private שאלה shayla he would not be more lenient but
if you're just putting something out for publication you're putting out the
more strict position. I do want to say one other interesting thing
about that about the sort of this phenomenon before we then go
back to the גמרא Gemara which is the idea of דרש, darash,
when he was דרש בפרקא. darash b'pirka. So דרש darash is an
interesting word to be used in conjunction with פסקנ'ינג, paskening, right? דרשה
drasha does not make it sound like we're talking about פסק. psak.
And actually, one thing that we have to appreciate is a phenomenon
that was probably, you know, certainly we know about in like through
some ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael material. I'm not sure if although רב
Rav actually came from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So anyway, which is
is that if anybody ever read the שאילתות, Sheiltot,
which is an early Gaonic work, but it's really it's really a
style of דרשות drashot which occurred which, you know, existed earlier in
the Amoraic period, which is that the standard way in which a
דרשה drasha was given in a שול, shul, which is you would
start with,
you would raise like a perhaps a halakhic question, and then you
would give a דרשה drasha and talk about some aggadic aspect or
whatever, and then you'd circle back, you know, to to the halakhic
question. So there would be an interweaving on something based on the
פרשה parsha about an aggadic aspect, like for example when it talks
about שרה Sarah dies and the מדרש Midrash and then יצחק Yitzchak
takes רבקה, Rivka, that the נר ner was דלוק, daluk, whatever. So
you start with that מדרש Midrash and then you talk about הדלקת
נרות hadlakas neiros on שבת, Shabbos. you know, and so on and
there was an interweaving of some type of a דרשה drasha on
the פרשה parsha together with a פסק הלכה. psak halakha. So that's
also possible what this phenomenon is referring to. But be that as
it may, what
I
find so interesting in light of our contemporary
experience in the
same גמרא Gemara here, on one hand we see רב Rav controls
the information as it were. But just before we
said what because he's not going to suppress, you know, somebody a
תנא's Tanna opinion.
In a theoretical conversation, right, when it comes to פסק, psak, right,
the תנא Tanna isn't ruling. Meaning I said the גמרא Gemara wouldn't
have I wouldn't I think have been so surprised if let's say
if the תנא Tanna was saying oh but שמואל Shmuel says otherwise,
right, because then it would have been a פסק. psak. Here it's
just like data. I mean there you actually do have cases, right,
where somebody tries to פסקנ'ן pasken like a different authority in the
presence of a competing authority that they actually are silenced and they
are offended. So I don't so there I think it's more about
like data rather than פסק. psak. But you are right at least
in terms of getting the information out there is it's not being
suppressed.
But this is also rabbinic arrogance of...
Well why do you call it arrogance rather than responsibility?
Well it is I think it's arrogance because משום עמי הארץ, mishum
amei ha-aretz. the assumption is that the average person will not be
able to handle something that's a bit of an exception and therefore
we'll just make it very simple and say you can't do it.
But we ourselves know in our own houses or whatever we can
do it. Right. That's true.
But
but I guess my question
is, I understand it's a double
standard, we rabbis can understand but they won't understand.
Okay, so it's definitely a double standard but it's only arrogance if
you think their assessment is wrong. If their assessment is right then
they're being responsible. Aren't they being responsible?
But you're turning people away. People may say that's ridiculous I can't
adhere to strict rules so I just...
Right I understand, I understand. I'm just not sure that it's arrogance.
I think, you know, it's a question about the types of trade-offs
that you make. Right, it's stricter than it needs to be, there
is a reality that some people will it'll be a slippery slope
and they'll misuse the קולא kula or whatever but on the other
hand if you're too strict you'll drive other people away. There are
competing values here. But again I and we might come out on
a different side of those values. I mean although they say because
of עמי הארץ, amei ha-aretz, so isn't that explicit?
רב Rav he throws
in עמי הארץ.
amei ha-aretz, No
I'm sorry the גמרא Gemara right משום shum עמי הארץ. amei ha-aretz.
Right I understand but that doesn't mean arrogance, it might mean responsibility,
at least how they're interpreting their responsibility. They feel they know that
if you give certain rulings it'll lead to more leniencies. There's definitely
cases where you
where I can tell you rabbis have very commonly had an experience
where if you tell somebody בדיעבד bediavad you can do this, all
of a sudden it becomes a לכתחילה lechat'chila if you make it
as a public announcement. If you give it to somebody as a
private פסק psak it's one thing, but you make a public announcement
בדיעבד bediavad this and this is allowed, right, for a lot of
people the בדיעבד bediavad part gets bracketed. Now you might still be
that that might be true but to respect your congregants you have
to allow for that mistake to be made rather than trying to
control and to infantilize them. Okay that's I think how a lot
of us would feel nowadays but it doesn't mean it's coming from
arrogance it might be coming from a sense of responsibility. You might
say a sense of responsibility that's shaped by arrogance but okay. Yes.
Or the situation a rabbi gives a private פסק psak leniently to
one individual because he felt that that person could deal with and
then that individual then tells the world and this rabbi gets the
reputation as the מיקל רב meikel rav and starts getting calls from
all over the world.
Exactly. Exactly.
Okay so two different verbs he's doing two different things, one he's
teaching and the other he's דרש.
darosh. Well that's why I was discussing that
verb. Maybe. Right. Okay, so anyway, all right, so let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara. says, ah, but at the end of
the day, back to our point, at the end of the day
we see that רב Rav rules like
rules leniently like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So why was he silencing
a תנא Tanna that quoted the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
if that's his basic ruling anyway? וכי תימא תנא בפירקא תנא, V'chi
teima Tanna b'pirka Tanna,
maybe this תנא Tanna was announcing the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir during the שבת Shabbos דרשה. drasha. So therefore, because he was
going to exactly the information that רב Rav was trying to control
was being let out of the bag during this דרשה. drasha. So
the גמרא Gemara says
he would reference something and then he'd turn to this תנא Tanna
and the תנא Tanna would announce.
Well, let's take a look, we'll read what and then I'll say
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, a תנא Tanna came, taught in
front of him, אטו, Atu, what do you think? כולי עלמא לתנא
צייתי? kulei alma l'tanna tzeisi? Are people listening to the תנא? Tanna?
No, לאמורא צייתי, l'Amora tzeisi, they're listening to the אמורא. Amora. Now
the אמורא Amora here does not mean רב. Rav. אמורא Amora was
also with a lowercase a if you would, the same way תנא
Tanna is a lowercase t, it's a functionary. And what the אמורא
Amora was was the loudspeaker. So basically here's how it would work.
Okay, here's the Rabbi giving the דרשה. drasha. Michael here is my
תנא Tanna because he remembers everything. So I, so we're talking about
מבשל בשבת, mevashel b'Shabbos, I say, Michael, what's the משנה? Mishnah? Thank
you very much, what's the ברייתא? Braita? Thank you very much. Okay,
he's my תנא, Tanna, he quotes those sources. But then I, there's
a thousand people here. I'm not going to strain my voice. So
I go ahead and I say it to Joe here who has
a very loud voice, right Joe? And Joe then proclaims it so
everybody can hear it. So Michael's my תנא, Tanna, Joe's my אמורא.
Amora. You guys are here because Joe is announcing it. So people
can't hear what Michael is saying. What? Yeah, exactly, people can't hear
what Michael is saying. They're listening to what Joe is saying. He's
my אמורא, Amora, so who cares if רב Rav has said רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir position? Okay, so let's take a look.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, תנא, Tanna,
here's the reason רב Rav silenced him. תנא שוחט קמיה, Tanna shochet
kamei, he didn't say המבשל בשבת, hamvashel b'Shabbos, he said השוחט בשבת.
hashochet b'Shabbos. That's what he said.
תנא קמיה דרב. Tanna kamei d'Rav. השוחט בשבת. hashochet b'Shabbos. If you
shecht on שבת, Shabbos. בשוגג יאכל במזיד לא יאכל. b'shogeg yei'achel b'meizid
lo yei'achel.
Different meaning or could be potentially because it's not everything is מבשל.
mevashel. Right. So then it was if it was בשוגג b'shogeg it
can be eaten, במזיד b'meizid it can't be eaten. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, so רב Rav said no, that's wrong, that's not that's the
correct an incorrect version of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
שחיטה shchita? is not the same as בישול. bishul. מאי דעתך, Mai
daitach, what are you thinking? כרבי מאיר, k'Rabbi Meir, that that's essentially
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. So if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it by בישול bishul he'll say it by שחיטה? shchita No. עד
כאן לא קשרי רבי מאיר, Ad kan lo kashari Rabbi Meir, when
does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir allow if you cooked בשוגג, b'shogeg, אלא
במבשל, ela b'mevashel, by case of cooking דראוי לכוס, d'ra'ui l'kos, that
the meat could have been the could have been chewed or the
vegetables could have been chewed raw. It's not a normal thing to
do, but at least it was able to be eaten. And therefore
it's not a מוקצה problem. It's only a problem about benefiting from
שבת Shabbos. violation and if it's בשוגג b'shogeg it's okay. That's רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. אבל שוחט, Aval shochet, but if you shechted
it, דאין ראוי לכוס, d'ein ra'ui l'kos, that it could not have
been chewed, you can't chew it off of the animal of animal's
living. Okay, so it's not fit to be eaten. לא, Lo, even
though it wouldn't be a מעשה שבת ma'aseh Shabbos problem, benefiting from
שבת, Shabbos. it would be a מוקצה problem. So finally we're coming
full circle where the גמרא Gemara just takes it for granted now,
which it was struggling all of yesterday, that you cannot eat this
meat on שבת Shabbos? even if there's no מעשה שבת ma'aseh Shabbos
problem because it wasn't fit to be eaten before שבת Shabbos. and
it's מוקצה. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והמתניתין דשוחט הוא? v'hamatnisin
d'shochet hu? One minute, our משנה Mishnah is talking about שוחט. shochet.
דאמר רב הונא ודרש חייא בר רב
משמיה דרב D'amar Rav Huna v'darsh Chiya bar Rav mishmei d'Rav and
we said that in the name of רב, Rav, אסורה באכילה
ליומא, asura b'achilah l'yoma, that you can't eat it on the day
itself. This is the same
רב. Rav. ונסבין חברייא למימר רבי יהודה היא, V'nasvin chavraya l'meimar Rabbi
Yehuda hi, and the students of the בית המדרש Beit HaMidrash said
this is according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda And we just got
through a whole long explanation that it was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
about benefiting from violation of שבת. Shabbos Why did we need all
of that? If you're telling me it's a מוקצה problem, which is
what we discussed yesterday. הא רבי מאיר שרי, Ha Rabbi Meir shari,
the implication is that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you can
eat this meat on שבת Shabbos; itself even if it was shechted
on שבת. Shabbos. So, and you're telling me that you can't eat
by שחיטה shchita because of מוקצה? גמרא Gemara says
כי שרי רבי מאיר, ki shari Rabbi Meir, when does רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir allow it? כגון שהיה לו חולה מבעוד יום, k'gon she'haya
lo choleh mi'be'od yom, that let's say it was ראוי ra'ui to
be eaten ערב שבת. erev Shabbos? How was it ראוי ra'ui to
be eaten ערב שבת? Erev Shabbos, In your house you had somebody
that was deathly ill. And therefore even when שבת Shabbos began, you
realized that you might have to shecht this cow to feed this
person meat on שבת. Shabbos So even though it was not yet
in its state to be eaten, it was planned and designated for
possible שחיטה shechitah on שבת. Shabbos So that would be a case
where you would not have a מוקצה problem, you would only have
a problem about benefiting from violation of שבת. Shabbos And now the
גמרא says one minute, if the case in the משנה Mishnah why
it wasn't מוקצה was because there was a person that was deathly
ill and therefore wasn't מוקצה, how are we going to get a
problem about violating שבת? Shabbos You're allowed to violate שבת. Shabbos So
the גמרא says אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's the case, מאי
טעמא דרבי יהודה דאסר? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda d'asar? Why according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda now is it forbidden because of benefiting from
violation? Who's violating? As כגון שהיה לו חולה והבריא. kigon shehaya lo
choleh v'hipri. Okay,
when שבת Shabbos began the guy was ill, so therefore you were
planning on שחט shechting this cow. Okay, it wasn't מוקצה. מוקצה is
determined by the beginning of שבת; Shabbos it doesn't change in the
middle of שבת. Shabbos. So when שבת Shabbos. began it was planned
to use this meat. Then שבת Shabbos. day he actually got better.
There was no need to שחט shecht it, and you went
ahead and
you שחט shechted it anyway. So there, there would not be a
מוקצה problem, but the problem according to רבי Rebbi יהודה would be
benefiting. Now I just want to point out the irony, right? All
of yesterday we were saying, oh, if you can't eat it on
שבת Shabbos. it's because of מוקצה. And we tried to show that
רבי Rebbi יהודה's position would have indicated that it's a מוקצה problem
and somehow we tried to say no, no, no, no, it's not
מוקצה. Now of course today, when we've established there is another רבי
Rebbi, יהודה that would explain why you can't eat it on שבת
Shabbos. because you're benefiting from שבת Shabbos, violation, now all of a
sudden we remember, hey, there's also a מוקצה problem here. So there
really are two problems: benefiting from שבת Shabbos, and מוקצה, and if
you want to say it's only one, it has to be a
special case where you thought where there was a חולה choleh and
therefore you have bracketed the מוקצה aspect. Okay.
The fact that you could have actually gone ahead and שחט shechted
it before שבת Shabbos, doesn't affect the, I mean, this idea of
of designating it for שחיטה shechitah on שבת Shabbos, before שבת. Shabbos
You could have done the שחיטה shechitah before שבת. Shabbos.
Oh, so why would it have been permissible to have been מחלל
שבת? mechallel Shabbos? So you have to assume that like, maybe he
would have needed, maybe he needs the fresh meat, or you weren't
certain whether, well I guess if you weren't certain you could have
prepared it before שבת. Shabbos, So you have to assume some case,
right, that you would needed the fresh meat. Right? Exactly. Okay, so
the גמרא says like this: וכי הא דאמר רב אחא בר אדא
אמר רב, v'hi d'amar Rav Achah bar Ada amar Rav, it's better,
וכי הא דאמר רב אחא בר אדא אמר רב. v'hi d'amar Rav
Achah bar Ada amar Rav.
So like רב אחא בר אדא Rav Achah bar Ada says again
in the name of רב, Rav, ואמרי לה אמר רבי יצחק בר
אדא אמר רב, v'amrei leh amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ada amar Rav,
השוחט לחולה בשבת, hashochot l'choleh b'Shabbos,
if somebody שחט shechts for a person who got sick on שבת.
Shabbos Now this is not a person who was sick ערב שבת,
Erev Shabbos although it's not clear, because it's a person who got
sick on שבת. Shabbos, So it's going to be a מוקצה problem.
You're allowed to שחט shecht because he's a חולה choleh and it's
סכנה, sakana, but he was not a חולה choleh before שבת, Shabbos
so it's still מוקצה for anybody else. Okay, so you שחט shecht
for חולה choleh on
שבת, Shabbos אסור לברי, assur l'bari, a healthy person cannot eat from
it because since he was not sick from before שבת, Shabbos it
was still מוקצה. So that's why a healthy person cannot eat from
it. המבשל לחולה בשבת, hamevashel l'choleh b'Shabbos, if you cooked for a
sick person on שבת, Shabbos, מותר לברי, mutar l'bari,
then a healthy person can eat it. Why? Because stuff you're cooking
is stuff that presumably although it was raw and not ideal was
somewhat edible and therefore is not מוקצה. מאי טעמא? mai taama? האי
ראוי לכוס, hai raui l'kos, the case of something cooked it was
fit to be chewed even though it was raw, והאי, v'hai, and
the case of the meat, אינו ראוי לכוס eino raui l'kos is
not fit to be chewed ערב שבת Shabbos when שבת Shabbos began.
So what he's saying is we have two issues: מוקצה and benefiting
from שבת. Shabbos, So if you did it for a sick person,
there's no violation of שבת, Shabbos there's no problem about benefiting even
for the healthy person to now say hey, you just cooked some
fresh food, great, I'll have it. Actually you have something like that
let's say guys in a hospital and they bring up some hot
food and the patient is too not feeling well enough to eat
it and you're there and you're spending the שבת with the patient,
can you eat from it because it was cooked for that person?
Okay, hey great you cooked some food, okay there's some extra, I'll
take some. So there's no problem about benefiting from violation of שבת,
right, because it was done for the sake of a sick person.
There is a problem of מוקצה and that depends on whether this
was somewhat fit to be eaten when שבת began. So those two
factors. Okay, so now we're going to finish this up, sort of
wrap up the details. אמר פפא, Amar Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
says, פעמים, peamim, there are times שחיטה מותר, shechitah mutar, that even
a case of שחיטה shechitah you can eat from the meat even
a healthy person. What? Like we said before, כגון שהיה לו חולה
מבעוד יום. kigon shehaya lo choleh mib'od yom. The person was sick
when שבת began. So if he was sick when שבת began, it's
not מוקצה, you were planning on שחט shechting it, and then you
went ahead and you שחט shechted it. It's not a violation of
שבת, the guy's a חולה, choleh, and therefore you can eat from
the meat. מבשל אסור, mevashel assur, and there are times when when
you cook it's forbidden even if you're cooking for a חולה choleh
for a healthy person to eat. Why? כגון שקצץ לו דלעת, kigon
shekatatz lo delat, like let's say you cut the דלעת delat from
the ground. Maybe it was מוקצה for another reason. Okay, it wasn't
fit to be eaten when שבת began because it was still growing
on the ground. Or תוספות says maybe it's a very very hard
דלעת delat that cannot, it's impossible to eat until you until you
cook it. So there are times where there will be where you
can change these realities, where a case of שחיטה shechita won't have
a מוקצה problem if you were planning on שחט shechting it because
the guy was sick, and a case of normal cooking will have
a מוקצה problem if the food was completely inedible before שבת began.
And now the גמרא wraps it up. אמר רב דימי מנהרדעי, Amar
Rav Dimi mi'Nehardai, רב דימי Rav Dimi from נהרדעי Nehardea said, הלכתא,
hilchesa, the הלכה halacha is, השוחט לחולה בשבת מותר לבריא באומצא. hashochot
l'choleh b'Shabbos mutar l'bari b'umtsa. If you שחט shecht for a sick
person on שבת, מותר לבריא באומצא, mutar l'bari b'umtsa, it's permitted for
a healthy person in אומצא. umtsa. Again and this is of course
a critical part is missing here but it means that the person
was sick when שבת *Shabbos* began so we don't have a מוקצה
*muktzeh* problem then a healthy person can eat it raw. Okay, can't
cook it obviously but can eat it raw. מאי טעמא *Mai taama*,
what's the reason? כיון דאפשר לכזית בשר בלא שחיטה shechita. כי שחיט
אדעתא דחולה קשחיט *Keivan deefshar lekezayis basar belo shechita ki shachit adaisa
dechola kashachit*. You can't get even one olive's worth of meat without
שחט shecht *shecht*ing a whole cow. So if I'm שחט shecht *shecht*ing
a cow and I'm giving some of the meat to the חולה
*chola* person, I did not do, I did not do and I
almost could not do any extra מלאכה *melacha* for the healthy person.
The reality is is there's going to be a ton of meat
as a result of my שחט shecht. *shecht*ing. I'm not doing anything
extra for the healthy person. So the חולה *chola* gets his meat
and if a healthy person wants to eat raw fresh meat he
can. It's not מעשה שבת *maaseh Shabbos* because there's no violation and
it's not מוקצה *muktzeh* as we're assuming the person was sick when
שבת *Shabbos* began. And you probably can't eat it if it's cooked.
We're going to say, המבשל לחולה בשבת *hamevashel lechola beshabbos*. However if
I'm cooking for a חולה *chola* person on שבת *Shabbat*, okay, now
the stuff wasn't מוקצה *muktzeh*, it was fit to be eaten before
שבת *Shabbat*, so you would think a healthy person can eat from
it. It wasn't מוקצה *muktzeh* and I didn't do a violation. Nevertheless,
אסור לברי *assur lebari*. A healthy person cannot eat from what I
cooked. Why not? גזירה gezeira שמא ירבה בשבילו *gezeira shema yarbe bishvilo*.
Because by cooking how much am I cooking? Am I cooking just
what the חולה *chola* needs? Am I cooking extra? So if I'm
cooking for a חולה *chola* and someone says great you've got some
extra food, it wasn't מוקצה *muktzeh* right? You didn't do a שבת
*Shabbos* violation. I'll eat from it. We'll say technically you're right. You
could eat from it. But if we let you eat from it
next time I have to cook for that חולה *chola* next שבת
*Shabbos* I might throw in a few extra pieces of meat and
a few extra vegetables because I know that you're going to want
to eat from it. And maybe even unconsciously subconsciously and so on.
So therefore I can't let you eat from it because that could
lead to me cooking more than is strictly needed and all that.
Yeah whatever. We just categorically forbid it.
So these are some parameters about concerns about גזירה שמא ירבה בשבילו
*gezeira shema yarbe bishvilo* about benefiting from a case even when it's
done for a חולה *chola* person. But I want to go back
for one minute to the debate of רבי Rebbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
and רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* because that's critically important because you
know the question about benefiting from חילול שבת *chilul Shabbos* how do
we rule? If it's בשוגג *beshogeg* רבי Rebbi, מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says
okay you can benefit from it. If it's but רבי Rebbi יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says no I'm sorry בשוגג *beshogeg* you have to wait
till מוצאי שבת *motzaei Shabbat*. And this definitely happens right? You'll go
to somebody's house and they they don't realize certain things and all
of a sudden you realize oh my God they just or whatever
I mean a real violation they just turned on the stove for
me or whatever but or they there could be things that are
more minor like they put the liquid back on the fire even
though it cooled off or whatever the case might be. Can I
eat from it? Okay so how do we rule? So the שלחן
ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* rules like רבי Rebbi, יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Even if
it's בשוגג *beshogeg* you have to wait till מוצאי שבת *motzaei Shabbat*.
The משנה Mishna ברורה *Mishnah Berurah* there says that he says בשעת
הדחק *beshaas had'chak* you can rely on because there's enough ראשונים *Rishonim*
תוספות *Tosafos* I think to be exact here who say that he
would go like רבי Rebbi.
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
and there's enough
ראשונים *Rishonim* that rule like
רבי Rebbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So בשעת הדחק *beshaas had'chak* you can
rely on the position that בשוגג *beshogeg* it's not a problem and
you can even benefit from it on שבת *Shabbos* itself. And that
actually becomes any type of thing like you'll offend the person, you're
going to you're not going to have any food to eat on
שבת *Shabbos* or whatever you're not going to be able to eat
from the meal. So and so that's number one very important ruling
and then the other important question becomes how do you define שוגג
*shogeg*? And how do you deal nowadays with people that are sort
of like not not orthodox and they know that according to orthodox
הלכה halacha. *halacha* it's forbidden but they don't buy into it, they
don't believe it's forbidden right? אומר מותר *Omer mutar*. So is that
also considered שוגג *shogeg* and can you also benefit from that? So
those are some interesting questions but it is important to know that
רבי Rebbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s position although not ruled on by the
שלחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* is a very there's a strong set of
ראשונים *Rishonim* that rule like רבי Rebbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and that
even the משנה Mishna, ברורה *Mishnah Berurah* tends to be pretty strict
says that it can be relied on בשעת הצורך *beshaas hatzorech*. Yes.
The case of someone who doesn't believe he's obligated how can we
eat that person's food even during the weekday? Because the person's a
מומר להכעיס *mumar lehachis*. Okay so that comes to questions about trust
and sort of somewhat similar questions as we had before and you
can imagine cases like that that or let's say they came into
your kitchen and they were a house guest and they went ahead
and they did something. Yeah I know you weren't going to do
it but I figured I'd be nice I turned on the stove
or I put what or who knows there are plenty of scenarios
okay? Alright so let's take a look at one more thing. So
we were saying that how can רב *Rav* say it was like
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* he has to hold like רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* what was our answer to that? Wasn't that our question at
some point? No our question was why did he silence the תנא
*tanna* and the answer no he says the משנה Mishna. *mishna*'s רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* doesn't mean he holds like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*.
Question was why did he silence the תנא *tanna* and at the
end it was the תנא דבי רבי *tanna debei Rabbi*. Okay so
there was no conflict with him saying the תנא דבי רבי *tanna
debei Rabbi* okay right. Okay let's take a look now. So now
we have had two משניות Mishnayos. *mishnaiot* about who can שחט shecht
*shecht*, two משניות Mishnayos *mishnaiot* about when you can שחט shecht *shecht*.
שחט shecht nighttime and on שבת יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and now
we go to what the knife has to look like. Let's take
a look. השוחט במגל יד, Hashocheit be'magal yad, if you שחט shechts,
with a hand sickle, בצור be'tzur or with a sharpened rock, ובקנה
u've'kaneh a sharpened reed, שחיטתו כשרה, shechitaso kesheira, the שחיטה's כשר. kosher.
Now the last two, the case where just you don't need a
formal כלי, which is something we mentioned right at the beginning as
long as it's smooth enough and sharp enough. The problem with a
sickle is that a sickle has serrated edges. Apparently, it has serrated
edges on the inside and not on the outside. So the point
is although there's serrated edges on the inside, you as long as
you're using the right side of it we're not making a גזירה
and we're allowing you to שחט shecht as long as you're using
the right side. Okay.
And now the משנה Mishna. says and this is quite interesting because
it basically is summing up the previous משניות. הכל שוחטין, HaKol Shochtin,
everybody can שחט. shecht That was our first משנה, Mishna even a
חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve'katan.
Okay, not a non-Jew, but even a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh
ve'katan. Okay, ולעולם שוחטין, u'le'olam shochtin, you can שחט shecht it anytime,
means whether day or night. That was the next משנה. Mishna ובכל
שוחטין, u'vechol shochtin, and you can שחט shecht with anything, even you
can use a rock and a reed. So you know these three
these three words sum up everything we've said until now. It's actually
possible that they don't sum it up, it's actually possible that they
reflect an early משנה. Mishna There might have been a very early
teaching that said הכל שוחטין, HaKol Shochtin, you know, what is it,
הכל שוחטין ולעולם שוחטין ובכל שוחטין. HaKol Shochtin u'le'olam shochtin u'vechol shochtin.
And then the משניות we just read were later elaborations of that
early phrase.
Okay, that's certainly a possibility. חוץ, Chutz, and the ובכל שוחטין u'vechol
shochtin you can שחט shechting with anything חוץ ממגל קציר, chutz mi'magal
katzir, you cannot use a type of a sickle used for harvesting
which is only serrated. It doesn't have a smooth side. והמגירה, ve'ha'magera,
which is like a saw, והשיניים, ve'ha'shinayim, or a
teeth taken from an animal, okay, והציפורן, ve'ha'tzipporen, or your fingernail, if
you sharpened your fingernail. Now most of these the problem is that
they're serrated. The fingernail is a different problem, but מפני שהן חונקין,
mipnei she'hen chonkin, and here it says
this is the phrase, the explanation why serrated is not good and
why the whole emphasis on the smooth knife with no nicks.
The assumption is that if there's a nick, then it's tearing, it's
not cutting. And tearing here is called חונקין, chonkin, they strangle the
animal, they tear rather than cut. And it has to be cut
by the sharpness of the knife. So anything that is serrated or
with a nick is not acceptable. Shouldn't the כהן Kohen kill the
bird? Yes, but with his fingernail. But that was also from the
back, that wasn't a שחיטה. Okay, that would not have been good
in any other case. Okay, so as the גמרא says it would
be a נבילה neveilah if it wasn't for the fact that it
was a קרבן. korban. Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. השוחט, Hashocheit, if one שחט, shechting בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא, bedieved
in lechatchila lo, it sounds like only בדיעבד be'di'eved can you use
these weird things, the stone and the reed and the hand sickle.
בשלמא במגל יד, Bishlama be'magal yad, I understand why a hand sickle
is only בדיעבד, be'di'eved דילמא אתי למעבד באידך גיסא, dilma ati le'me'evad
be'idach gisa, we're concerned that if we let you use the smooth
side you'll come to use the serrated side. אלא צור וקנה לכתחילה
לא? Ella tzur ve'kaneh lichatchila lo? But when it comes to a
rock or a reed you're telling me that לכתחילה lichatchila you can't?
Maybe because they're not like nice vessels? But who said? והרמינהי, Ve'ha'raminihi,
I'll ask you on this, בכל שוחטין, bechol shochtin, we have a
תוספתא Tosefta that says you can שחט shechting with everything and again
here it's לכתחילה, lichatchila, not if you did it it's כשר, kosher,
but you can. You can שחט shecht with everything and what's included
in that list? בין בצור, bein be'tzur, whether a rock, בין בזכוכית
bein be'zechuchis or glass, בין בקרומית של קנה, bein be'krumis shel kaneh,
whether by like the type of the hard part of a reed.
So you see that as long as you sharpen it and make
it into a functional smooth knife, you can do it even לכתחילה.
lichatchila. So why would our משנה Mishna use the בדיעבד be'di'eved, language,
the post-facto language, if it's allowed לכתחילה? lichatchila? So the גמרא says
לא קשיא, lo kashya, that's not difficult. כאן בתלוש כאן במחובר. kan
be'talush kan be'mechubar. It matters whether it is detached or attached. If
it is detached then you can do it. If it's attached then
we are going to see tomorrow that something that is attached to
the ground even if it's sharp and you cut it and so
on is only acceptable בדיעבד be'di'eved not לכתחילה. lichatchila. We'll see why
tomorrow, but that's at least how we're explaining that our משנה Mishna
that is בדיעבד be'di'eved is that you when you have a rock,
it's not like a rock you pick up in your hand. You've
got a huge boulder, you sharpened an edge and maybe you took
a cow to it and you like moved the cow's neck rather
than moving the thing. That's what you have to do if it's
מחובר, mechubar, you have to move the animal rather than the thing.
Okay, or the reed bend it and move it. The reed maybe,
not the rock. Anyway, so the גמרא says like this, so let's
read a little more. Okay, where are we? דאמר רב כהנא, De'amar
Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana said, השוחט במחובר לקרקע, hashocheit be'mechubar
le'karka, if you שחט shecht something that's still attached, רבי פוסל, Rebbi
possel, רבי said it's invalid, ורבי חייא מכשיר, ve'Rabbi Chiya machshir, רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya says it's valid, but that's only post-facto. עד כאן
לא מכשיר רבי חייא אלא בדיעבד, ad kan lo machshir Rabbi Chiya
ella be'di'eved, so when רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said it's good it's
only after the fact. אבל לכתחילה לא, aval lichatchila lo, but not
at the beginning. Who did you say it's going like? To רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya בדיעבד? be'di'eved It's like רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and
it's בדיעבד? bedieved? But I'm going to show you that there is
those that say that if something is attached, it's good even לכתחילה.
lechatchila. And והא תניא, v'ha tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Braita,
בכל שוחטין, bakol shochtin, you can שחט shechts, לכתחילה lechatchila with anything,
בין בתלוש בין במחובר, bein b'talush bein b'mechubar, whether detached or attached.
בין שהסכין למעלה וצואר בהמה למטה, Bein shehasakin lemala v'tzavar behema lemata,
whether the knife is above and the animal's below, meaning basically the
animal's on the ground, so the knife is above the animal and
you're שחט like that. בין שהסכין למטה וצואר בהמה למעלה, Bein shehasakin
lemata v'tzavar behema lemala, or the knife is below the animal, meaning
the animal's standing up and it's always coming from this part of
the neck. But the question is where is the animal? Is the
animal on the ground and you're שחט like that, or the animal
standing and you're שחט underneath? The concern of the other case is
that maybe the weight of the animal's neck if it's standing puts
pressure
on the knife and it's not just the sharpness
of the knife, but no, that's allowed as well. So you see
you can שחט no matter how the animal's standing and you can
even שחט if the thing is attached. So that's even לכתחילה. lechatchila.
So that that we just taught, מני, manni, who is it going
like? לא רבי, Lo Rebbi, it's not רבי who says בדיעבד bedieved?
it's no good, ולא רבי חייא, v'lo Rebbi Chiya, and not רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya for רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya was only בדיעבד. bedieved
אי רבי חייא, Ee Rebbi Chiya, because if it's רבי חייא, Rebbi
Chiya, בדיעבד אין לכתחילה לא, bedieved in lechatchila lo, he says only
בדיעבד bedieved. it's good if it's attached. אי רבי, Ee Rebbi, and
if it's רבי, בדיעבד נמי לא, bedieved nami lo, even בדיעבד bedieved
it's not good. So the גמרא says לעולם רבי חייא, le'olam Rebbi
Chiya, you're right, it is רבי חייא. Rebbi Chiya. ואפילו לכתחילה, V'afillu
lechatchila, you're right, I take it back, רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya says
even if it's attached you can do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. So now
we're back to our question. והא דקמיפלגי בדיעבד, V'hada kamifligi b'bedieved, and
why would they debate him and רבי by a case of בדיעבד?
bedieved לאודועיך כוחא דרבי, L'odiacha kocha d'Rebbi, to show you that רבי
invalidates even בדיעבד. bedieved? But רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya will say it's
good even לכתחילה. lechatchila. So now we're back to square one. Our
משנה Mishna says only בדיעבד bedieved. you can use this rock. If
it's רבי, you could not even בדיעבד bedieved it would be no
good. If it's רבי חייא, Rebbi Chiya, it's good לכתחילה. lechatchila. So
why is our משנה Mishna saying you can only use the rock
בדיעבד? bedieved ואלא מתניתין דקתני השוחט, V'ela matnisin d'ktani hashochet, our משנה
that says השוחט, hashochet, if one שחט, בדיעבד bedieved? אין לכתחילה לא,
in lichatchila lo, only בדיעבד, bedieved, מני, manni, who is that? לא
רבי ולא רבי חייא, Lo Rebbi v'lo Rebbi Chiya, it's not רבי
or רבי חייא. Rebbi Chiya. אי רבי חייא אפילו לכתחילה, Ee Rebbi
Chiya afillu lechatchila, and now it's a little repetitive, if it's רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya it would be good even לכתחילה. lechatchila. אי רבי,
Ee Rebbi, if it's רבי, בדיעבד נמי לא, bedieved nami lo, it
would even be no good בדיעבד. bedieved. So we're back to our
question. There is a debate if you can use something attached. But
the one who says you can says even לכתחילה. lechatchila. So our
משנה that says you can a rock is good only בדיעבד, bedieved,
who is that going like? So the גמרא says לעולם רבי חייא,
le'olam Rebbi Chiya, it is רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and ואפילו לכתחילה
afillu lechatchila and you can do it even לכתחילה. lechatchila. ומתניתין דקתני
השוחט רבי, U'matnisin d'ktani hashochet Rebbi, and our משנה that says השוחט,
hashochet, that says you can use the rock only בדיעבד, bedieved, that's
רבי. One minute, we just said רבי said בדיעבד bedieved it's no
good. So the גמרא says קשיא דרבי ארבי, kashya d'Rebbi a'd'Rebbi, so
רבי is contradicting himself, is he good בדיעבד bedieved or not? לא
קשיא, Lo kashya, and this is what last line we'll read for
today, כאן במחובר מעיקרא כאן בתלוש ולסוף חיברו. kan b'mechubar meikara kan
b'talush u'lisof chibro. There are two types of what something means to
be attached. This has a lot of implications in a lot of
areas of הלכה. Something that was always attached to the ground, it
was planted and it grew from the ground, it was a cave,
it was whatever, you know, a tree, something that was always attached
from the ground or something that started as detached and then was
attached, like a house, like if I took a knife and I
inserted it into a wall and plastered it over, if I built
a wall, all those are things which is תלוש, talush, once was
detached and now is attached, and that does not have the same
status as fully being attached. So when does רבי say that if
you use something attached it's בדיעבד bedieved no good? That's when it
was always attached. When does he say that when you use something
attached לכתחילה lechatchila don't but בדיעבד bedieved it's okay? If something started
detached and then was attached afterwards. So we will discuss this tomorrow,
but these are the three opinions relating to things that are attached
to the ground.